Guide to the Clare Leighton Papers, 1940-1968 RL.00803
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clare Leighton papers
1940-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leighton, Clare, 1898-1989
RL.00803
5.8 Linear Feet
Clare Ellaline Hope Leighton was an English printmaker who immigrated to the United States in 1939. The Clare Leighton Papers date from the mid-twentieth century and include woodblocks, preparatory prints and drawings, engravings, and correspondence related to Leighton's artistic practice.
594 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Clare Leighton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Biographical Note
Clare Leighton was born in England in 1898. She studied at Brighton College of Art and the Central and Slade Schools in London. Leighton is best known for her books of stories and illustrations of agrarian subjects and the American South. The artist was a member of Duke University's Department of Art, Aesthetics, and Music from 1943 to 1945 and was awarded several prizes for her artistic achievements.
For more information, see Hickman, Caroline. "Clare Leighton and the American South." Duke Library Magazine Vol. 17, No. 3 (Spring/Summer 2004).
Collection Overview
The Clare Leighton Papers document Leighton's artistic production, and particularly her illustrations for the book Southern Harvest, published by the Macmillan Company in 1942, and The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore, a seven-volume series published by Duke University Press from 1952-1964.
Materials in the collection include printer's proofs, preparatory sketches and prints, sketches, engravings, and a limited amount of correspondence related to the publication of Southern Harvest, the printing of Under the Greenwood Tree, and to the acquisition of the Clare Leighton Papers.
Illustrated books -- History -- 20th century; Wood-engraving -- 20th century; Women artists; Leighton, Clare, 1898-1989 -- Southern harvest; Duke University -- Faculty
- Woodblocks, 1940-1968, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  The Woodblocks series contains a number of Leighton's blocks used for her wood engravings.
  - Wood Engraving Blocks (Box 1)
    Corn Husking, Baptizing, Fishing in Creek, Tobacco Barons, Sorghum, Coon Hunt, All Day Singing, Quilting Party, Herb Gatherers, Washing Clothes, Cockfight, Weeding Tobacco Bed, Dante Bookplate, Still, Wreck (block broken), Village Lovers, Windblown Tree, Cotton Picking, Centenarian, Chopping Cotton, Cotton Pickers, Spring House, Catfish, Cypress Swamp, and Mountain Girl
- Preparatory Materials, 1940-1968, 2 boxes
  This series contains preparatory sketches and various sizes of prints. Some of these materials were used in the preparation of Leighton's book, Summer Harvest, and for her illustrations in the volumes of The Frank C. Brown Collection of North Carolina Folklore and Henry David Thoreau.
  - Bird Designs, Mural Polaroids (2), Assorted Small Prints, Bookplate Exhibition Materials (1967) (Box 2)
  - Preparatory Prints and Drawings for North Carolina Folklore (Box 2)
  - Preparatory Prints and Drawings for Southern Harvest (Box 2)
  - Printer's Proofs for Southern Harvest (Box 2)
  - Untitled Field Scene (Slide, Photo, and Negative) and Studies for Corn Shucking and Southern Harvest (1942) (Box 3)
  - A House Near Durham (Print and Accompanying Text) (Box 3)
  - Preparatory Prints, Drawing, and Proofs for illustrations of editions of Henry David Thoreau's Walden, Cape Cod, and The Maine Woods (Box 3)
- Engravings, undated
  Scope and Contents
  The 94 plates, signed by the artist, vary in size and are mounted and inlaid in heavy paper mats. Numbered as set 2, 42 engravings were used to illustrate the artist's book Southern Harvest. 1942. Two of these plates, Tobacco market at night, show the process for making an engraving. Numbered also as set 2, 16 plates illustrated The time of man, by Elizabeth Madox Roberts. 1945; 24 plates, The Frank C. Brown collection of North Carolina folklore. 1952-54. Twelve plates, New England industries, which are numbered set 4, were designed for Josiah Wedgwood & Sons, Ltd.
  - In the Time of Man engravings (Box 5)
    Engravings entitled: Ellen, Planting tobacco, There were rolling hills, Sheltering from the rain, Apple harvest, Gathering brush, Lovers in the Wheatfield, Winter, She lay there all day, The top of the rise, Jasper's hog pen, Ellen hoeing, Ellen with her baby, The house at Phillip's place, Ellen with her children, Tobacco barn, Some better country.
  - North Carolina Folklore by Frank C. Brown engravings (Box 5)
    Engraving titles include: The baptizing, Carolina wreck (Hatteras wreck), Cat fish (Fish caught), Centenarian, The cockfight, The coon hunt, Corn shucking in the mountains, The cotton choppers, Cotton pickers, Cypress knees, Dragging nets, Fishing in the creek, Flue curing tobacco, Herb gatherers, Moonshining, Mountain girl, Mountain haystacks, Mountain springhouse (Springhouse), The quilting, Singing in the mountains (All day singing), Sorghum boiling, Washing clothes, Weeding the tobacco seed bed, Wind and pine (Windblown tree)
  - New England Industries engravings (Box 5)
    Engravings include: Cod fishing, Cranberry gathering, Farming, Grist mill, Ice cutting, Lobsters, Logging, Maple sugar, Marble quarry, Shipbuilding, Tobacco, Whaling
  - Southern Harvest engravings (Box 6)
    Engraving titles include: Alabama barn, Alabama hog pen, Apple butter, Aunt Madge, Child mother, Chopping wood, Cinnamon ferns, Corn shucking, Cotton, Cotton picker, Cotton "telescope," Cotton picking, Cypress tree in flood, Dog tooth violet, Ear of corn, Hog killing, Hurricane in a cornfield, Louisiana pilgrimage, Magnolia, Mountain miller, Old clothes stall; Old Ollie, Old Sam, Pitcher plants, Po' white cabin, Po' white woman, Smoke house, Song of praise to dead hog, Sorghum mill, Tobacco, Tobacco barns, Tobacco loopers, Tobacco Market at night, Tobacco worm, The Reverend Hill's dream, The Rev. Hill walks away, Trillium, Tulip poplar bud, Waterfall in flood, Water mill, Weighing cotton, Woman with tin bath, [Two sheets of initials]
- Correspondence, 1940-1968, 1 folder
  The Correspondence series includes limited documentation of Leighton's publication of Summer Harvest, as well as some materials related to the acquisition of the Clare Leighton Papers and art objects by the Rubenstein Library.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1968 (Box 2)
  - Blank greeting cards from Leighton, approximately 1945-1960s (Box 2)
    Three greeting cards, unsent: a flower, a mother and baby, and a snow scene. Inside each is the message "Greetings from Clare Leighton"; two are from Durham, N.C., and one is from Woodbury, Conn.
- Other Works, 1 box
  This series contains materials relating to Clare Leighton's other artistic works.
  - Photographs of East Duke Building mural (Box 4)